in this episode my climbing Journey
continues as I'll be trying out one of
the purest forms of climbing Trad
climbing the aim being to get me on the
sharp end for the first time on a
multi-pitch climb that I've never seen
before all within my first year of
climbing this is TR
climing it would be truly mental to try
this sort of thing without a
professional so I've recruited the
world's best Pete Whitaker from the
YouTube channel white boys is one of the
most accomplished TR Climbers on the
planet it's really hard to highlight
just how strong p is but his list of
hard climbs says all particularly his
first Descent of Crown Royale graded 9A
possibly one of the hardest Trad routes
ever climbed go check out the wide boys
Channel if you want to see more of
Pete's style of crack climbing goodness
but before we go any further what is
Trad climbing Trad is short for
traditional climbing before people
started putting bolts into rocks the
only way up was free sowing or placing
some temporary protection on the Rock in
case you fall the leader will have to
place these pieces of gear and there's a
real skill to doing it so that they hold
however Trad opens up opportunities as
to what you can climb you're not
confined to what someone has done before
you can climb whatever you like really
provided you've got the Courage the
first thing Pete thought to show me was
how to play gear into the Rock if you're
going to fall you want to know you won't
hit the ground and therefore proper
placement of gear is essential so we're
going to look at gear placing cuz that's
the crucial part of Trad climbing yeah
this is the bet I'm worried about keep
yourself safe yeah we have a bunch of
friends these are called friends they're
going to be your friend okay have you
ever seen them before I've seen them
like on the like for sale in the
climbing Mall never seen anyone use them
never seen them out in the wild never
seen them in wild Pete showed me how to
place a camming device into parallel
cracks in the wall the skill is in
finding a good place for the cam using
the right size cam and doing it smoothly
enough so that you don't fall off while
placing the thing if the placement is
solid these things can lift a car but if
not even a little bit of rope drag can
walk them out of the wall we found one
it's just interesting to think that this
can hold your weight right cuz it's
pretty small and this is they get much
SM they get tiny these CS key chains
right uh they can do yeah like with the
basics explained there was no better way
to see how it was done than to watch a
master so Pete led a climb and I
followed removing the gear as I went to
see what he did just a little note here
watch Pete climb easy grades here for
him this is a walk in the park he could
probably climb this blindfolded with one
hand and one foot but he still climbed
really smoothly with very careful
movements just as he would with a 9A
climb probably because I'm Bing him
anyway I just thought that was
interesting yeah feeling good feeling
good I mean it's always easy on the to
say you're feeling good on the top rope
right top rope tough guy top rope tough
guy that's what I am the route was a
really nice mellow slab with lots of
places for gear as I removed pieces I
tried to note where and how they were
placed
nice yeah good yeah that was fine yeah
yeah that's a piece of cake piece of
cake the next job was to climb the route
again and practice placing the gear on
the way up did he put a big huge cam in
there I think he
did
just want everyone to know that I don't
condone
[Applause]
that that's solid Pete then had a look
at my gear placement to see how I got
on so that was a that was a
bomit that one's good but I'd say we can
do
better so I think I put a gold in here
when I was uh leading it I think it was
in there so I put
it I put it in left in the wide section
and then slid it into the narrower
section
there I think that is probably slightly
better that one we can see is like a bit
flaring
um could be better a little bit further
back there he was a bit a little bit on
the
edge ah yeah so this was the place where
it was like a little bit more
tricky I mean it's it's pretty good that
maybe there is a bit slight yeah I think
slightly to the right is a better
placement it's just a bit narrower for
the cam size you can see how the cam
lobes on the left hand side are are
really good but on the right hand side
they're really
open it's kind of
like a recipe for a ripping cam there's
so many other good choices around here
that we should use the good
choices so Pete yeah you've had a look
at Mike's uh Mike's gear placements what
are your thoughts U my thoughts are well
I said uh before that I was like
65% um happy maybe a bit more I mean the
good placements were absolutely really
good and it's a route that you could do
just on those placements um but I would
quite like Mike to place a few more
pieces um and those are the pieces that
are in between the good ones uh so
they're a little bit more marginal yeah
it just takes a long time to know which
flaring slot to put the cam in which way
up to put it um and where are the best
spots so I practice placing the gear
again this time the placement was much
better and Pete seemed much happier yeah
that one is very difficult to go wrong
with this placement um yeah absolute
bomber like way way better way better
than the first go nice yeah and even
found a a bit in the middle one in the
middle which uh ien found so there you
go it's a good
one with all of that out the way there
was nothing left to do but to lead the
climb for real right Kim we good right
climbing clip the right hand rope here
yeah
good
I was pretty Cal and collected here I
knew what gear to place where and all
the placements were really solid however
I was chilled out because I knew I
wouldn't fall the route was very easy
and if I climbed carefully I'd be
[Music]
fine piece of
kick
[Music]
that was
scary however Pete wasn't going to let
me call this challenge done that easily
he told me to book a flight to Norway to
find out if I'd really learned anything
from him the final goal would be to
climb a multi-pitch Trad route and we'd
be on sighting it too which means
neither Pete nor me would have climed it
before all we'd have is the guide book
and I'd be leading the first and last
pitch here the nerves definitely kicked
in I had no idea what was ahead of me so
a fall was plausible here my gear
placements would have to be solid and I
have to manage gear so I didn't leave
too much space between cams or Worse use
them all in the first 15 M and have to
climb to the end of the pitch
unprotected that would be bad but before
we watch me freaking out about that a
quick word from this week's sponsor the
thing I love most about climbing is when
you strike the perfect balance of
difficulty and fear and you enter the
Flow State suddenly it's just you and
the wall and you're completely and
utterly focused it's meditative and it
feels incredible you could get yourself
into that state anytime you like by
meditating I've been using this episode
sponsor headspace to do just that for 4
years now for me meditation is just 10
minutes a few times a week before bed
listening to one of the wind down
meditations you can pick from three to
10 minutes here so the trick here is
when your mind starts to wander from the
meditation and it inevitably will rather
than just throw in the towel and quit
gently pull your focus back to the
meditation that's the trick to it after
a few times of doing this just a few
times a week you'll be so good at this
skill that you'll notice yourself
utilizing it in everyday life like when
your cam rips out of the rock you can
learn to use this control to make
situations much more relaxed headspace
also has 90 minute long Focus tracks
from the likes of Han Zimmer they also
have Bedtime Stories and various sounds
for sleeping too as well as yoga videos
I would describe it as the ultimate
mindfulness app you can try headspace
for 60 days for free using the code down
in the description or scanning the QR
code on screen now thanks to headspace
for sponsoring the video right back to
[Applause]
it I've got nerves nerves now
yeah suddenly I need a
poo but my harness is on so I'm just
going to have to
wait do you ever think like what am I
doing me yeah no when you're claiming no
no um okay predictions are we going to
get wet yes or no yes Mike yes I'm
already
wet smash
it
fuing
[__] the first opportunity to place gear
was 3 m up and it wasn't exactly a great
[Music]
placement right at the bottom of the
Flop yeah y you going in properly
yep you're I can all good
yep with a really solid second piece my
nerves eased up a little bit and I could
carry on with the
climb
okay
what bad piece in
[Music]
there nice very
good I'm not far off a
g f like I've been claiming for
[Music]
hours
after some cruisy climbing with plenty
of gear I was at the top of the pitch
all right Pete that's me
safe you can take me off
be good job mate we should do here is
admire Mike's
impeccable rope
management you see green rope perfectly
on the left orange
rope perfectly on the right they haven't
crossed a single time it's like a pro
Pete then LED pitch two which I was
grateful for as the climbing was much
harder I've just climbed pitch number
two and that was actually a little bit
more tricky I think that could be a
tricky second for Mike actually I'm be
really interested to see what he thinks
when he comes up to the top of that one
[Music]
that was
hard manage all the climbing yes I did
yeah you did yeah that's a really good
effort yeah I thought it was I like I
thought it was climbing well there big
layback and a jam and a roof and it was
a mess and it was great it was brilliant
I loved it yeah good full on proper
multi-pitch style we're swinging leads
yep you're taking next lead yep sharing
the load sharing the load so you don't
get too tired
exactly and you're going to blast to the
top it's going to be epic right
climing back on the lead for the final
pitch my confidence was
high until this
happened I just wrapped straight out
is on Pitch number three and he has just
tested a piece of gear and ripped it out
it's always a little bit unnerving when
you put a piece in you think it's good
and then you obviously tug on it and
then it just rips straight out which I
think is what you may have just done I
really wasn't keen on going into the
unknown with that crappy gear placement
this is not going well okay come on
let's stay calm here
luckily I managed to maintain composure
enough to find something
[Music]
better that's
bad after that Fiasco The Climb became
super easy with Gorgeous views and The
Summit in sight I could chill a little
[Music]
bit good not coming
this is how to learn to Trad climb with
a professional looking over your
shoulder there's just so much more that
can go wrong here than with sport
climbing but with someone who's
experienced on the job you can safely
get a taste of what TRD is all about the
adventure we're
alive good job nice
one the only thing that remains is how
do we get back
[Music]
down